Good morning, we are, it is, today's דף daf *Daf* is דף
מ"ה *Daf Mem Hei*, 45. We pick up on the bottom of
דף מ"ד עמוד ב' *Daf Mem Dalet Amud Bais*. We just read
the משנה mishna *Mishna* of the last, first משנה mishna: *Mishna* of
the last פרק perek. *Perek*, where we're moving to the final thing
about things that are said בלשון הקודש *B'lashon Hakodesh* and it is
עגלה ערופה eglah arufah *Egla Arufa*, the recitation of the, that the
elders do, when they, after the breaking of the neck of the,
this calf for the, the murderer that they, for this murdered victim
that they cannot find, they don't know who the murderer was.
And we'll see some interesting ways in which at the end, it
will tie back to certain parallels with the סוטה sotah *Sota*. I
mean obviously the first thing is is that there's a question of
doubt. In the one case, you sort of, you don't know if
the woman committed adultery; here you know what happened and you don't
know who it is who did it. So anyway let's take a
look now at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, okay? So it started by
saying, the משנה mishna *Mishna* started by saying, עגלה ערופה egla arufa
*Egla Arufa* you say בלשון הקודש *B'lashon Hakodesh* and it quoted a
פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk*, כי ימצא חלל ki yimatzei chalal, *Ki Yimatzeh Chalal*,
which doesn't seem to have anything to do with the fact that
it's said in Hebrew. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, three lines
down in the wide lines here: מאי קאמר *Mai Ka'amar*? What is
the משנה mishna *Mishna* saying? How does the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* have
anything to do with the fact that you're saying it in Hebrew?
אמר רבי אבהו הכי קאמר *Amar Rabi Abbahu Hachi Ka'amar*, here's what
it says. שנאמר וענו ואמרו *Shena'amar V'anu V'amru*, it says by the
sages, by the עגלה ערופה egla arufa, *Egla Arufa*, they shall respond
and say: ידינו לא Lo. שפכו את הדם הזה *Yadeinu Lo Shafchu
Es HaDam HaZeh*, our hands did not spill this blood. ולהלן הוא
אומר *U'lehalan Hu Omer*, it says by the לויים *Levi'im*, by the
ברכות וקללות *Brachos and Kelalos* of הר גריזים והר עיבל *Har Gerizim
and Har Eval*, which is one of the standard sources of things
that are said in Hebrew, וענו הלווים ואמרו *V'anu HaLevi'im V'amru*, and
the לויים *Levi'im* shall respond and say. מה ענייה האמורה להלן בלשון
הקודש *Ma Aniyah Ha'amura L'halan B'lashon Hakodesh*, the same way there it's
in Hebrew, as we know from previous discussion, אף כאן בלשון הקודש
*Af Kan B'lashon Hakodesh*, here too it's in Hebrew. So meaning the
משנה mishna, *Mishna* really did not tell you the source that it's
in Hebrew, that's some other source, it's וענו ואמרו *V'anu V'amru*. The
משנה Mishna *Mishna* quoting the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* of כי ימצא חלל
chalal, *Ki Yimatzeh Chalal* is really getting onto point number two. סדר
עגלה ערופה eglah arufah, כיצד *Seder Egla Arufa Keitzad*, now talking about
an עגלה ערופה eglah arufah. *Egla Arufa*, what is the procedure of
the עגלה ערופה eglah arufah. *Egla Arufa*? כי ימצא חלל chalal *Ki
Yimatzeh Chalal*, let's start looking at the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*: if there
is a corpse found on the ground, ויצאו v'yatze'u, זקניך ושופטיך zekanecha
veshoftecha *V'yatzu Zkeinecha V'shoftecha*, the elders and the judges go out, שלשה
מבית דין הגדול שבירושלים היו יוצאין *Shlosha MiBeis Din HaGadol ShebeYerushalayim Hayu
Yotzin*, three from the central בית דין Beis Din? *Beis Din* of
ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim* were exiting. So yes it's true, the משנה Mishna.
*Mishna* really does not address לשון הקודש *Lashon Hakodesh*, it really is
סדר עגלה ערופה egla arufa. כיצד *Seder Egla Arufa Keitzad*, what is
the story with the עגלה ערופה egla arufa, *Egla Arufa*? לשון הקודש
*Lashon Hakodesh* is just learned out from the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* of
וענו ואמרו *V'anu V'amru*. Okay and now we turn therefore to the
first issue in the משנה *Mishna*, which is, it's בית דין הגדול
Beis Din Hagadol. *Beis Din HaGadol* representatives of the central court because
it's ויצאו זקניך ziknecha? ושופטיך V'shoftecha, *V'yatzu Zkeinecha V'shoftecha*. Later the פסוקים
psukim *Psukim* say that it's זקני ziknei העיר ההיא *Ziknei Ha'ir Hahi*,
the elders of that city that is close, but first you have
to measure and determine which is the closest city, so to remind
you the פסוקים *Psukim* say: ויצאו זקניך ושופטיך ומדדו v'yatze'u ziknecha v'shoftecha
u'madadu, *V'yatzu Zkeinecha V'shoftecha U'madadu* סביבות החלל *Svivous HaChalal*, what's the פסוק
pasuk *Pasuk*? מן העיר אשר סביבות החלל *Min He'ir Asher Svivous HaChalal*
or something I can't remember the exact פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk*. Anyway it
says that they, the elders, measure to the nearby cities and they
determine the nearby town, and then the elders of the nearby town
come out and they perform this whole ritual. Okay so
the central elders are the
ויצאו זקניך ziknecha, ושופטיך v'shoftecha *V'yatzu Zkeinecha V'shoftecha*, not the זקני העיר
*Ziknei Ha'ir*, they are the ones from the
בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol, *Beis Din HaGadol*. Now how many
are there? So the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* said three and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* said five. So let's see what that
debate is. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר חמשה *Rabbi Yehuda Omer Chamisha*,
five. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*: ויצאו זקניך ziknecha ושופטיך v'shoftecha
*V'yatzu Zkeinecha V'shoftecha*. זקניך ziknecha, *Zkeinecha*, שנים *Shnayim*, two, it's in plural.
ושופטיך v'shoftecha *V'shoftecha*,
שנים *Shnayim*, two. ואין בית דין Beis Din. שקול *V'ein Beis Din
Shakul*, you don't have a בית דין Beis Din. *Beis Din* that's
an even number because in order to represent a בית דין beit
din, *Beis Din* it has to be an odd number there has
to be a deciding vote, so even though they're not voting on
anything here or who knows maybe there'll be a debate which city
was really closer, but anyway even if it's not voting on anything,
for a בית דין beis din *Beis Din* to be a model
a representative of a בית דין beis din. *Beis Din* it has
to have that structure of an odd number, so מוסיפין עליהם עוד
אחד הרי כאן חמשה *Masifin Aleihem Od Echad Harei Kan Chamisha*, you
add one that's five. דברי *Divrei* רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*,
that's what רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* said. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon אומר *Rabbi Shimon Omer*, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* who
is the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* of our משנה *Mishna*, says: No.
זקניך ziknecha *Zkeinecha*, שנים *Shnayim*, we don't count ושופטיך v'shoftecha *V'shoftecha*. We
just say זקניך ziknecha *Zkeinecha* is two. ואין בית דין beis din.
שקול *V'ein Beis Din Shakul*, you don't have an even number. מוסיפין
עליהם עוד אחד הרי כאן שלשה *Masifin Aleihem Od Echad Harei Kan
Shlosha*. Okay, so that's the debate of three and five. Now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks the obvious question: ורבי שמעון V'Rabbi Shimon, נמי
הא כתיב ושופטיך v'shoftecha? *V'Rabbi Shimon Nami Ha Ksiv V'shoftecha*? What does
he do with the fact that
it says the judges? ההוא מיבעיא ליה למיוחדים שבשופטיך *Hahu Mibaya Lei
L'meyuchadim Shebishoftecha*. ושופטיך V'shoftecha *V'shoftecha* is to tell you your special judges,
meaning your singular judges, meaning the ones from the בית דין הגדול
Beis Din Hagadol *Beis Din HaGadol*. So that word is not adding
to the number but it's identifying that it's the central judges, the
ones from the בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol *Beis Din HaGadol*.
ורבי יהודה *V'Rabbi Yehuda*, ורבי יהודה *V'Rabbi Yehuda* learns it from זקני
זקניך ziknei ziknecha *Ziknei Zkeinecha* נפקא *Nafka*. The fact that it could
have said זקני *Ziknei* and it says זקניך *Zkeinecha* or it could
have said זקנים zekeinim *Zkeinim* and it says זקניך *Zkeinecha*, yours means
your special ones, your distinctive
ones. the ones from the high court. So you don't need שופטיך
shoftecha? to tell you the high court. ורבי שמעון, now what does
רבי שמעון rabbi shimon, do with the possessive of זקניך? אי כתיב
רחמנא זקני, Ei ksiv rachmana ziknei,
had it just written elders, הוה אמינא אפילו זקני השוק, hava amina
afilu ziknei hashuk, I would have thought it meant like old people
that you find in the marketplace. I wouldn't have thought it meant
like judges, I would have thought it meant literal old people. כתב
רחמנא זקניך, Kasav rachmana ziknecha, so it says the possessive "yours", there's
something special about their status, which means that they're judges, but I
still wouldn't have known yet that they are from the בית דין
הגדול. Beis Din Hagadol, ואי כתב רחמנא זקניך, V'ei kasav rachmana ziknecha,
if it had just said זקניך, so I would have known it
meant judges, but I would have said הוה אמינא אפילו סנהדרי קטנה,
hava amina afilu sanhedri ktana, it would have been a smaller court.
כתב רחמנא ושופטיך. Kasav rachmana v'shoftecha. ושופטיך, v'shoftecha סנהדרי קטנה, sanhedri ktana,
סדרי קטנה?
sidrei ktana? I mean like a local בית דין?
beis din, A local, yeah, yeah, meaning yes, it's for like a
tribe, it's not for, or for a major city, but it's not
the central בית דין. beis din. Exactly, it's twenty-three, it's not seventy-one.
כתב רחמנא
ושופטיך, Kasav rachmana v'shoftecha, so זקניך the possessive means they're special, they're
actually judges, and ושופטיך means they're your central judges, they're the בית
דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol המיוחדין שבשופטיך. hamiyuchadin shebeshoftecha. Okay,
but not to add to the number. ורבי יהודה נמי זקני זקניך
גמר זקני מזקני העדה. V'Rabbi Yehuda nami ziknei ziknecha gamar ziknei miziknei
ha'eidah. מה להלן מיוחדין שבעדה אף כאן מיוחדין שבעדה. Ma lehallan miyuchadin
sheba'eidah af kan miyuchadin sheba'eidah.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda now we're going to drop the idea
that the ושופטיך tells you that it's an extra number because presumably
he also needs to go two stages: first to prove it doesn't
just mean old people and then to prove it means the סנהדרין.
Sanhedrin. So the גמרא Gemara says: You know what? You're right. He
gets the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, the idea of סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, not from זקניך,
he gets the idea of סנהדרין Sanhedrin from this other פסוק, pasuk.
זקני העדה, ziknei ha'eidah, which is a פסוק when the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
rules incorrectly and people follow
them and they have to bring a special קרבן korban in ויקרא.
Vayikra. How many of the בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol. has
to show up to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash to bring the
קרבן? korban? So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda learns over there that you
only need five, you don't need the whole בית דין beis din.
הגדול to show up. So the גמרא Gemara is saying: Oh, so
if he learns זקני זקניך from עגלה ערופה egla arufa there, then
you don't need ושופטיך to tell you five, right? He was learning
זקניך is two, ושופטיך is two, but if you learn from that
זקני that we're talking about בית דין beis din הגדול, you should
also learn five members of the בית דין beis din. הגדול because
that's what we say there as well. So למיגמר לכולה מילתא מהתם,
lemigmar lekulah milta mehatam, learn everything from there, זקניך ושופטיך למה לי?
ziknecha v'shoftecha lamma li? Why do you need ושופטיך? So the גמרא
gemara says: Fine, let's go back to what we were saying before.
We don't learn it out from there. Everybody agrees that זקניך the
possessive tells you we're not talking about old guys, we're talking
about שופטים. shoftim.
ושופטיך tells you you're talking about the ones from the סנהדרין הגדול,
Sanhedrin Hagadol, you're not talking about a local בית דין. beis din,
So how does he get to five?
ושופטיך למניינא. V'shoftecha leminyana. Okay, the extra ו, vav, it could have
said זקניך שופטיך. ziknecha shoftecha. If it was, because actually it makes
a certain sense, right? You know, sometimes the תורה Torah has two
words without the ו vav that sort of like, you know, they're
describing the same entity. So if it would say זקניך שופטיך, ziknecha
shoftecha, it would mean "your zekeinim who are your shoftim." And that
would have told me זקנים from the בית דין beis din, הגדול.
The extra ו vav tells me to count the word ושופטיך as
a separate unit and to get me two more. ושופטיך למניינא. V'shoftecha
leminyana. ורבי שמעון ו vav לא משמע ליה, lo mashma lei, and
רבי שמעון is not impressed by the ו. vav. And therefore that's
the whole debate. Okay. אלא אמר גמרא Ella amar Gemara top of
מה עמוד א. mem hey amud aleph. אלא מעתה, Ella me'ata,
ויצאו שנים ומדדו שנים, v'yatze'u shenayim u'madadu shenayim, why don't we say
ויצאו זקניך ושופטיך ומדדו, umadadu that they will go out and they
will measure. So why don't we say that those verbs actually also
are in the plural so that should add two more? ויצאו שנים
מדדו שנים, V'yatze'u shenayim madadu shenayim, so that gives you four more.
Of course the funny thing is like what else is the פסוק
supposed to say? If it says they go out and they measure,
you can't say "v'yatzei", I mean anyway. So the גמרא gemara says
why don't we say הרי כאן תשעה, harei kan tishah, לרבי יהודה
הרי כאן תשעה, l'Rabbi Yehuda harei kan tishah, so you add four
more, so that gets you nine for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda, ולרבי
שמעון הרי כאן שבעה. u'l'Rabbi Shimon harei kan shiva. גמרא Gemara says
no, ההוא מיבעי ליה, hahu mibayei lei, that you need it, I
don't know why you don't just need it for it to tell
you what it's telling you, but לכדתניא, lichdetanya, like we teach in
a ברייתא: brayta: ויצאו, they go out, הן ולא שלוחיהן, hen v'lo
shlucheihen, only they and they can't send messengers or, you know, representatives
to do the measuring for them. ומדדו umadadu they measure, שאפילו נמצא
בעליל לעיר she'afillu nimtza ba'alil la'ir even if it was like obvious
that it was like right outside of a city and there was
no question which was the closest city, היו מודדים hayu modedim they
would still measure. You have to do the measuring even if you
know, שמצוה לעסוק במדידה shemitzvah la'asok bemedidah there's a mitzvah to do
the act of measuring. Okay, so anyway that's how we learn out
the יצאו, yatzu, ומדדו they have to do it personally, they have
to do the measuring even if they know, and the זקניך ושופטיך
tells you either three or five. Five.
You had a technical use of the word מצוה, mitzvah, it's a
מצוה לעסוק במדידה, mitzvah la'asok bemedidah, in other words if I were
to count מצוות mitzvot I would have to count...
No, I mean the whole idea, the whole enterprise of counting תריג
מצוות taryag mitzvot is something in the time of the ראשונים rishonim
or whatever. Exactly. Yeah, no, it means that it's a requirement. Okay,
מתניתין matnitin says the גמרא Gemara דלא כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. delo
k'rabbi eliezer ben yaakov. Our משנה is not like רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב. rabbi eliezer ben yaakov. Why not? דתניא תנא בריתא, detanya tana
beraita, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, rabbi eliezer ben yaakov omer, זקניך
זו סנהדרין, zekanecha zo sanhedrin, שופטיך זה מלך וכהן גדול. shoftecha ze
melech vekohen gadol. So actually it says none of this three or
five, we're going to get this is a major enterprise here. Okay,
it's pretty powerful the idea, you know, it's already powerful the idea
that in some local village there was a dead body that you're
going to go to the main court of the land and have
representatives of the main court of the land, like what that means
in terms of taking communal or national
responsibility for such a thing, right? And here, right, so I mean
it's a very you know powerful image and here he says not
only that we're going to get all the leaders to take responsibility,
okay? The king, the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, the political leader, you
have the courts, the political leader, the religious leader, everybody is taking
responsibility for how can this be that there was this, you know,
that there was this murder that occurred. Which is by the way
also pretty funny if you think about it because it's not the
fact that a murder occurs, the fact that a murder occurs you
deal with that locally. You send it to the local בית דין,
beis din you know, you have the you know you have the
perpetrator, you execute him or whatever you do, but somehow and you
can help me understand this, the fact that we don't know who
it is, I mean I guess the fact is not just that
a murder occurred but that we have to deal with the fact
that we haven't resolved it, you know, that we have this unresolved
guilt about it, right? Because we haven't been able to punish the
right person, right, that has to be like something that's like at
a national level dealing with that sense, right? And that's clearly what
the ritual is about, ונתכפר להם הדם, venitchaper lahem hadam, like, you
know, if the פסוק says, you know, כי לארץ לא יכופר בדם
אשר שפך בה כי אם בדם שופכו, ki la'aretz lo yechupar badam
asher shupach bah ki im bedam shofcho, there'll never really be atonement
until justice is meted out. So what does it mean not just
that this crime has occurred but that atonement
and justice has not been served? So for him, you don't just
take the סנהדרין, sanhedrin, you take all the leaders, you take the
political leader, the religious leader. So one minute, so he says זקניך
זו סנהדרין, zekanecha zo sanhedrin, שופטיך זה מלך וכהן גדול. shoftecha ze
melech vekohen gadol. מלך, melech, how do you know מלך melech is
שופטיך? shoftecha דכתיב, dechativ, מלך במשפט יעמיד ארץ. melech bemishpat yaamid aretz.
So משפט, mishpat, so שופטיך shoftecha means the king, obviously that's the
law of the land, he represents order. כהן גדול, kohen gadol, דכתיב,
dechativ, ובאת אל הכהנים הלוים ואל השופט אשר יהיה בימים ההם. uvata
el hakohanim haleviyim veel hashofet asher yihyeh bayamim hahem. Which is interesting
because there you might say it identifies שופט shofet distinct from כהנים,
kohanim, but nevertheless he's saying שופטיך shoftecha. is also the role of
the כהנים, kohanim, so they're also about you know justice, maybe representing
God's rule in that sense of law and justice, but that the
כהן kohen is also part of שופטיך. And then the גמרא Gemara.
just asks a question, so if you have the king and the
כהן גדול kohen gadol and the סנהדרין, sanhedrin, what do you mean
by the סנהדרין? sanhedrin? איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
במלך וכהן גדול הוא דפליגי, rabbi eliezer ben yaakov bemelech vekohen gadol
hu depligi, is he only arguing about the king and the כהן
גדול? kohen gadol? אבל בסנהדרין, aval besanhedrin, when it comes to who
constitutes the סנהדרין, sanhedrin, אי כרבי יהודה אי כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה,
ei kerabbi yehuda ei kerabbi shimon sevira lei, he holds like רבי
יהודה rabbi yehuda or רבי שמעון, we're talking about three or five,
we're not talking about the entire סנהדרין. sanhedrin. או דלמא, o dilma,
or since he just says זקניך סנהדרין zekanecha sanhedrin and right it
sounds like maybe he means the whole סנהדרין. sanhedrin. או דלמא בסנהדרין
נמי פליגי o dilma besanhedrin nami pilgi and דאיכא כולה סנהדרין, de'ika
kullah sanhedrin, he means the whole סנהדרין, sanhedrin, which would be consistent
with the idea that he wants to get everybody taking ownership of
this. So if you're going to get the king and the כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, maybe not just a representative of the סנהדרין, sanhedrin,
maybe the entire סנהדרין sanhedrin turns out. Tov, you had a question?
No, I was just going to say, I
think this is like a major, like the whole, I'm wondering like
why is this little niggly concern how you get three or how
you get five, because it's a major dispute when there's an anonymous
death of a single human being, is it the localized problem of
some obscure community? Right. Or is it a national crisis? A national
crisis that there's an anonymous death of a single human being. Think
how huge an issue in the consciousness of
social responsibility.
It's like a huge statement here. No, I agree, I agree, and
I think that obviously רבי אליעזר בן יעקב rabbi eliezer ben yaakov
here is taking it obviously to a whole next level. And if
you think about it, the סוטה
situation is also something is unresolved, and it's not addressed locally, you
know, you have some little village
somewhere in the
middle
of nowhere and they go to the central. they get God involved
in it, right? They go to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
So there is obviously a comparison here of the unresolved nature of
these things. Yes, Jenna? Yeah, there's kind of like
the fear that goes along with it, right? Of not knowing that
there's a murderer somewhere in the midst.
Oh, that's a good point, too. Right, there's a murderer out there,
and someone you don't know. It's easier when it's like, oh, they're
a bad guy and I can point at them, but when we
don't know who it is, it's much scarier. That's a very interesting
point. Does the dead body have to show a sign of being
violently murdered? Yes, we're going to get to that. It might actually
even be violently murdered in a particular way. So we'll get to
that in a little bit. Okay. Does it have to be some
kind of connection between measurement and self-introspection in some way? Oh, the
whole idea of measuring is the metaphor for taking stock of
how did we allow this? Oh, that's a nice point. That's why
the מצוה mitzvah specifically is במדידה. be-medidah. Like we were sloppy until
now, and the whole idea of precision and taking stock or whatever,
like this happened maybe out of a certain degree of lack
of attention. Right, that's a very nice point. Okay, so גמרא Gemara.
says like this. Okay, so now, does רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov say you need the entire סנהדרין? Sanhedrin? So what's
the story? So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב יוסף,
Amar Rav Yosef, תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here, and this
is going to be an interesting analogy or whatever, לימוד. limud. מצא
זקן ממרא אביי פגי. Matza zakein mamrei abei pagi. Now, we're going
to another story about that involves the entire סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, which is
זקן ממרא, zakein mamrei, right? When there's an elder who defies the
ruling of the central court and goes ahead and he teaches and
preaches and practices a הלכה halacha against the central court. And he's
the זקן ממרא zakein mamrei and he's put to death. So let's
say he finds the court not in their the לשכת הגזית lishkas
ha-gazis in their special room in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but
he finds them אביי פגי. abei pagi. Now, אביי פגי, abei pagi,
not exactly clear what those words mean. רש״י Rashi says it means
somehow in the belt, like in the environment, like in the city
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim.
in the environs
of the city, but not in
their actual official official room in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So
he finds them elsewhere in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim נמצא Nimtza where were we?
מצא זקן ממרא אביי פגי והמרה עליהם.
Matza
zakein
mamrei abei pagi ve-himrah aleihem. And he rebelled against them, right? He
gave his opinion, they disagreed with him, then he went back to
his town and he
preached his opinion and he taught people to do like his opinion.
Okay, so the dispute occurred though not in the לשכת הגזית. lishkas
ha-gazis. יכול תהא המרתו המראה? Yachol tehei hamraso hamraah? Maybe that would
be considered a rebellion and he would be put to death? תלמוד
לומר וקמת ועלית אל המקום אשר יבחר. Talmud lomar ve-kamta ve-alisa el
ha-makom asher yivchar. Right, where the whole פסוק of זקן ממרא zakein
mamrei starts by going to this central court, to the place that
God has chosen, and they will tell you what the law is.
So to the place. מלמד שהמקום גורם. Melamed she-ha-makom goreim. The place
determines. They have to be coming from their actual location in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash to have to represent their full status as
representing God's law so that the rebellion against them would be fully
symbolically significant. Okay, so they teach a הלכה halacha there, and then
he goes home and preaches against them specifically against להחטיא את הרבים.
le-hachti es ha-rabim. I don't know no, he's not just להחטיא את
הרבים, le-hachti es ha-rabim, he thinks he's being מצדיק את הרבים. matzdik
es ha-rabim. But the point is he's defying their authority. He thinks
they're wrong, they're sinners, they're mistreating, teaching everybody. From his perspective of
what the official teaching was. Yes, but I wouldn't say להחטיא, le-hachti,
I wouldn't say that's his purpose. Okay, anyway. And the problem is
also less that he's making people sin, the problem is more that
he is defying and undermining their authority. That's the whole problem of
the זקן ממרא. zakein mamrei. All right, so anyway, but it says
okay, דנפקי כמה? De-nafki kamah? Now, how many people did he discover
outside of the לשכת הגזית lishkas ha-gazis that they had this exchange?
Okay, how many people left the לשכת הגזית? lishkas ha-gazis? אילימא דנפיק
מקצתם, Ilimah de-nafik miktzasam, let's say a subset of them? Yes, a
subset of them, a minority of them? So דאמרי הנך דאיכא גואי
כוותי סבירא להו. de-amri hanach de-ika gavai kvasai sevira lehu. So first
of all, of course he's not a זקן ממרא. zakein mamrei. If
he's only disagreeing with a subset of the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, maybe the
rest of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin agrees with him. How does he know
that this is the official ruling of
the סנהדרין? Sanhedrin? It's pretty funny because who's saying that they're making
their decision now? Maybe they're reporting a decision that had been made
earlier. But anyway, if he's not disagreeing with the whole סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
of course he's not a זקן ממרא. zakein mamrei. So אלא פשיטא
דנפקי כולהו. ella peshita de-nafki kulhu. It must be that they all
left, or at least a majority of
them left. He has to be the only הוה אמינא hava amina
that he could be a זקן ממרא zakein mamrei is if he's
debating the entire סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
or at least the majority of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. ולמאי? U-le-mai? Now
we have to understand,
one minute, what justified the entire סנהדרין Sanhedrin to leave their official
room? Their official chamber. אי לדבר רשות, Ei li-devar reshus, if they're
who knows, they're going out to see a movie. So מי מצי
נפקי? mi matzi nafki? They're not allowed to leave their chamber in
their official capacity, I mean at the end of the day, but
you can't stomp doing or for דבר רשות, dvar rishus, וכתיב vachisiv
שררך אגן הסהר אל יחסר המזג, sarech agan hasohar al yechsar hamazeg,
your navel is like a round goblet, the mixed wine shall not
be lacking. Okay, so what does that mean? So this is seen
as a metaphor for the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. שאם נצרך אחד מהם לצאת,
she'im nitzrach echad meihem latzeit, so we learn out somehow that this
represents the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. רש"י Rashi says because the idea of the
round goblet is that the סנהדרין Sanhedrin would sit in like a
semicircle. Semicircle. Right. The moon shape. The moon shape, exactly. So if
that's true, okay, and therefore if the first part refers to the
סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, what does אל יחסר המזג, al yechsar hamazeg, the mixed
wine shall not be lacking, mean? שאם נצרך אחד מהם לצאת, she'im
nitzrach echad meihem latzeit, if one
of them had to go out for whatever reason, are you allowed
to leave? אם יש שם עשרים ושלושה כנגד סנהדרי קטנה יוצא, im
yeish sham esrim ushlosha kineged Sanhedrei ketana yotzei, if you're leaving behind
you a twenty-three that at least represents the full authority
of a high court and you're not the highest court is seventy-one,
but the full authority of a court that could prosecute capital cases
is twenty-three. So if you're leaving behind twenty-three, יוצא, yotzei, you can
go out. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, but if you're leaving behind less,
it's like walking out of a room, you know, and then there
won't be a מנין minyan left behind, if you leave out and
there won't
be twenty-three, אינו יוצא, eino yotzei, you can't go out.
Now, what does that have to do with אל יחסר המזג? al
yechsar hamazeg? Because they would mix wine a one to three ratio.
So twenty-three is about a third of seventy-one. I mean, you know,
whatever, how exactly we get, but it's close, okay, so rounded down
or something. Anyway, so therefore we learn out that you can't have
less than a third remains. All right. So if that's true, if
they were just going for דבר רשות. dvar rishus. Now, I don't
exactly understand
the question. So they went for דבר רשות dvar rishus and they
left twenty-three behind and there were still forty, what is this, forty-eight
of them, sixty, like forty-eight
of them. So anyway, I don't exactly understand why it says that
they can't have gone out for דבר רשות, dvar rishus, all they
had to have done was left twenty-three behind. There was one part
wine, three parts water? What? Yeah. Anyway, but maybe to understanding that
it wouldn't be enough for the זקן ממרא zaken mamre to debate
even the majority
of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. It's assuming the זקן ממרא, zaken mamre, even
for there to be a הוה אמינא, hava amina, would have to
debate the entire סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So anyway, how did they leave? If
they can't certainly the entire סנהדרין Sanhedrin can't leave for דבר רשות.
dvar rishus. So how did they leave? But rather, you know, I
gotta tell you that like there's a type of thing like you
would expect תוספות tosafos to discuss and I have been meaning to
mention it the last few days, you might have noticed but the
דפים dapim are a lot bigger, like a lot more text on
the דפים dapim because there's no תוספות. tosafos. And why there's no
תוספות, tosafos, if you look back, I've been meaning to say this
like on the bottom of מ"א ע"ב mem aleph amud bet of
mem... where was it... of מ"ב ע"ב, mem bet amud bet, it
says מאלו התוספות לא מצאתי יותר, me'eilu hatosafos lo matzati yoser, which
means that you know what the publisher did, it wasn't that there
was always like a pre-determined תוספות tosafos that went with a גמרא.
Gemara There were different תוספותים tosafosim like now there's a תוספות הרא"ש
Tosafos Harosh and there's a תוספות רבנו פרץ Tosafos Rabbeinu Peretz and
you know there are these different תוספותים tosafosim that emerged from different
schools. And he found a manuscript for the most complete or the
best quality תוספות tosafos he could find and that's the one that
was published with the גמרא. Gemara Which is why actually if you're
interested to know on any given מסכת masechet which תוספות tosafos it
is, like from which school it is, אורבך's Ourbach בעלי התוספות, Baalei
Hatosafos, so the whole ninety percent of the book is all just
discussing the schools
of
the בעלי התוספות, Baalei Hatosafos, the personalities etc. but he has a
chapter at the end where he goes מסכת masechet by מסכת masechet
and he identifies what is the school of the תוספות tosafos of
that מסכת. masechet. It's not the same across מסכתות. masechtos. So anyway
this publisher's manuscript ran out, you know, in the middle of this
פרק. So for the last few דפים dapim we don't have any
תוספות tosafos and we have bigger דפים. dapim. Anyway, so I don't
exactly get why it couldn't say that he encountered forty-eight of them
and they left twenty-three behind, but some reason the גמרא Gemara is
assuming that he had encountered the entire סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So the entire
סנהדרין Sanhedrin could not have left דבר רשות. dvar rishus. So why
did they leave? אלא פשיטא לדבר מצוה, ela peshita lidvar mitzvah, it
must be that they left for a מצוה mitzvah purpose. What would
be a מצוה mitzvah purpose they would leave for? למאי לאו למדידת
עגלה רבי אליעזר בן יעקב היא. lemai lav lemedidat egla Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov hi. Ah, it must be they went for the עגלה
ערופה eglah arufah, and that's the only מצוה mitzvah purpose we can
think of for the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So that shows you that according
to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, you would need
the entire סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Of course, the funny thing is is that
like so what, the חכמים chachamim would not have that scenario
of him encountering them outside, it would only be a scenario for
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב? Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov? But okay, that's what
the גמרא gemara wants to say, maybe we see that there is
a position that the entire סנהדרין Sanhedrin you need for עגלה ערופה,
eglah arufah that's the position of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov. So the גמרא gemara says אמר אביי לא. amar Abaye
lo. No, that doesn't have to be the reason they left. דאזלו
להוסיף על העיר ועל העזרות. de'azlu lehoseef al ha'ir ve'al ha'azarot. You
sometimes need a סנהדרין Sanhedrin to do other things like maybe they
went to expand the boundaries of ירושלים Yerushalayim, or of the עזרות
azarot of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash because in order to define
the area
of
קדושה, kedusha, you know, what is the
קדושת kedushat of
the בית המקדש... Beit Hamikdash...
space is sanctified with the קדושה kedusha
of
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, what space is sanctified with the
קדושה kedusha
of
ירושלים, it comes through a ritual that involves the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. כדתנן,
ki-de-tnan, like we taught in the משנה: אין מוסיפין
על העיר ועל
העזרות אלא בבית דין של
שבעים ואחד,
ein mosifin al ha-ir ve-al ha-azarot ela be-veit din
shel
shivim ve-echad, you do not expand the city or the עזרות azarot
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash אלא בבית דין של שבעים ואחד,
ela be-veit din shel shivim ve-echad, you need all 71 of them.
So we really do not know whether according to רבי אלעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov you needed the entire סנהדרין Sanhedrin for
the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah but now we actually have a ברייתא
braita that teaches it. תניא כוותיה דרב יוסף, tanya kevateih de-Rav Yosef,
we taught like רב יוסף: Rav Yosef: מצאן
בית פגי והמרה עליהם, matzan Beis Pagi ve-himrah aleihem, if the זקן
zaken found the סנהדרין Sanhedrin outside
of
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and he rebelled against them so והמרה
עליהם.
ve-himrah aleihem.
כגון, kegon, now what's the example
this ברייתא braita says that they were outside the בית המקדש?
Beis HaMikdash? כגון שיצאו למדידת עגלה או להוסיף על העיר ועל
העזרות.
kegon she-yatzu li-medidat eglah o le-hosif al ha-ir
ve-al ha-azarot.
They left for the
measuring of the עגלה eglah or to add to the city or
the עזרות. azarot. יכול תהא המרתו המרה, yachol tehei hamrato hamrah, maybe
that would be a rebellion and he'd be a זקן ממרא? zaken
mamre? תלמוד לומר וקמת ועלית מלמד שהמקום גורם. talmud lomar ve-kamta ve-alita
melamed she-ha-makom gorem. So what this ברייתא braita adds is it gives
us the scenario that they left, that they left for the עגלה
ערופה. Eglah Arufah? So it doesn't mean that's the only scenario, but
it gives it as a scenario. And the only one who now
we have said is of that opinion that it makes sense, you
know who would say that, is רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov, which is very consistent with רבי אלעזר בן יעקב’s Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov position, right? רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov wants the entire leadership to take ownership of this issue. So
for him it's the כהן גדול kohen gadol and the מלך melech
and for the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, not just a representative of the סנהדרין,
Sanhedrin, but the entire סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Yes, I just want to a
really brief clarification. So in this ברייתא, braita, מצאן בית פגי והמרה,
matzan Beis Pagi ve-himrah, in other words, he found them in session,
right, in their place, in that? Yeah, it's not clear. Are they
in session, or are they just standing around measuring and he's talking
to them? Right, but then what's the כגון? kegon? What do you
mean כגון? kegon? It's like the chamber, it's like all together but
outside. Right, how did he find them outside of? What's the scenario
that he found them? Not what's the scenario that he was rebelling,
what's the scenario that he found them out outside of when he
was rebelling against them? Yeah, I mean his rebellion consists of him
going back to his town and preaching. But the exchange where he
voiced his views and they overrode him? They were already in the
lobby on their way. Exactly, exactly. Was he a member of the
סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, the rebellious זקן? zaken? Yeah, he could have been, or
he could have been a minor of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. They all
had to go to measurement, he left with the עגלה. eglah. Well,
he could have been a part of that, but he doesn't have
to have been a member of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. He could also
be, he could be like of that of that stature, but not
a member. Yeah, like you see, the סנהדרין Sanhedrin is like a
firematic siren. Yeah, the what? Firematic siren. Yeah, the fireman, when they
want to go shopping or grocery, whatever it is, that they all
have to go with the
truck and all be there because just in case they get a
call. Oh, interesting. Like they ran out and they had to go
buy yogurt together. The firemen. That's wonderful. We're all gone for ice
cream. Okay. בואו נמשיך. bo’u namshich. Okay, all right, very good. Okay,
נמצא טמון nimtza tamun now. So that's how many of the סנהדרין.
Sanhedrin. Now we get to the scenarios which will call for the
עגלה ערופה. Eglah Arufah? So if he's found buried, נמצא טמון בגל,
nimtza tamun be-gal, buried under a pile of like bricks of stone,
או תלוי באילן, o taluy be-ilan, or suspended from a tree, you
know, hanging from a tree, you would not do it. It has
to be נופל באדמה, nofel ba-adamah, right? He has to be like
on the ground and exposed. So הגמרא ha-Gemara says, לימא מתניתין רבי
יהודה ולא רבנן, leima matnitin Rabbi Yehuda ve-lo Rabbanan, unless our משנה
is רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda and not the רבנן. Rabbanan. דתניא, de-tanya,
as it was taught in a ברייתא: braita: ושכחת עומר בשדה. ve-shachachta
omer ba-sadeh. It's a good, it's a bad thing Charlie isn't here.
Charlie's been learning, you know, זרעים Zeraim or whatever, he would really
enjoy today's דף and discuss עומר, omer, a good שכחה, shichachah, excuse
me, you know, שכחה, shichachah, right, we're not the לקט leket part
but and פאה, pe’ah, yes, שכחה, shichachah, we're going to so ושכחת
עומר בשדה, ve-shachachta omer ba-sadeh, so you forget a sheaf in the
field. פרט לטמון, perat le-tamun, so what does that mean? Let's say
you forgot it, but you forgot it because it was buried under
something, was buried under some straw, was buried under a blanket. Is
that considered שכחה? shichachah? So רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda says no, בשדה
ba-sadeh means exposed. וחכמים va-Chachamim say בשדה, ba-sadeh, no, it doesn't mean
exposed, it means like even in the field, even like buried in
the field, לרבות את הטמון, le-rabot et ha-tamun, to include something buried.
So it seems like our משנה that says that it says נופל
בשדה, nofel ba-sadeh, it has to be exposed, that seems to like
link up with רבי יהודה, rabbi yehuda right, who says בשדה ba-sadeh
means visible and exposed. That's what he says by שכחה. shichachah. So
the גמרא gemara, says, אמר רב אפילו תימא רבנן, amar Rav afilu
teima Rabbanan, no, it can even be the רבנן Rabbanan that say
by שכחה shichachah that it can be buried. Here they would admit
that it needs to be exposed. What's the difference? הכא מעניינא דקרא
והכא מעניינא דקרא. hacha me-inyana de-kra ve-hacha me-inyana de-kra. In each time
we learn we look at the פסוקים contextually. דכתיב. de-chtiv. There, here
it says כי ימצא חלל, chalal, if you find a corpse. So
before I got to the word בשדה, basadeh, what would my assumption
have been? היכא דמשתכח, heicha demishtakach, wherever it's found. There's nothing limiting,
I would have been very expansive. And then it adds the words
באדמה, ba'adamah, oh I think I was saying בשדה, basadeh, excuse me.
Anyway, כי ימצא חלל באדמה ki yimatzei chalal ba'adamah on the ground.
So that extra word, if I was already going to be inclusive,
is coming to limit. פרט לטמון, perat letamun, that would say that
it has to be exposed, and if it's not exposed, you don't
apply these laws. So that's because I would have started broad, so
the word באדמה ba'adamah narrows me. והתם מעניינא דקרא, vehatam me'inyana de'kra,
there the context is different. דכתיב, dechtiv, כי תקצור קצירך בשדך, ki
tikzor ketzircha besadecha, when you cut your, you know, your harvesting, you're
cutting in the field, ושכחת עומר בשדה, veshachachta omer basadeh, and you
would forget a sheaf. So ושכחה דומיא דקציר, veshichcha dumya de'katzir, so
the forgetting is juxtaposed to the act of cutting, of harvesting. מה
קציר בגלוי אף שכחה בגלוי. ma katzir begalui af shichcha begalui. So
the same way the cutting, the grain is exposed, so the word
ושכחת veshachachta I would have interpreted in a similar context, that it's
out in the open and it's exposed. So there I would have
started narrow. I would have started to say only if it's exposed.
כתב רחמנא בשדה, ketav rachamana basadeh, and then it adds a word
בשדה, basadeh, that must be coming to expand it, לרבות את הטמון.
lerabbot et hatamun. Okay, so the word באדמה ba'adamah or בשדה basadeh
does not in itself mean exposed or buried. The question is, it's
understood to be in contrast to what I would have assumed until
I hit that word. So by the case of the corpse I
would have assumed broad, the word narrows me. By the case of
שכחה shichcha I would have assumed narrow, the word broadens me. Okay,
so
now the גמרא Gemara says, רבי יהודה נמי תיפוק ליה משכחה דומיא
דקציר. rabbi yehuda nami tipok lei mishichcha dumya de'katzir.
One minute. If the juxtaposition of forgetting and cutting and harvesting suggests
that it's exposed, then why did רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda need the
word בשדה basadeh to tell you it has to be exposed? Right?
We're talking about the עומר, omer, the שכחה. shichcha. Let him just
say the fact that it's compared to the harvest tells you it's
exposed. אי הכי נמי, ei hachi nami, you know what, you're right.
He really didn't need the word בשדה. basadeh. Everybody agrees that the
פסוק there by שכחה shichcha starts with the idea of exposed because
of comparison to cutting, to harvest. ואלא בשדה למה לי? ve'ela basadeh
lama li?
So then why does רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda need the word בשדה?
basadeh? What does that do for him once he already knows it
means exposed? The רבנן rabbanan say בשדה basadeh limits, it, oh I'm
sorry,
the רבנן rabbanan say בשדה, basadeh, excuse me, expands, it doesn't have
to be exposed, even buried. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, that says
before I got to the word בשדה basadeh I knew it had
to be exposed, and he demands that it be exposed, what does
he do with the word בשדה? basadeh? So the גמרא Gemara says
ואלא בשדה למה לי? ve'ela basadeh lama li? מיבעי ליה לרבות שכחת
קמה. mibaei lei lerabbot shichchat kama. Let's say I don't forget a
cut sheaf, let's say I forget two cut, some of the standing
grain. Standing grain, standing grain, right.
So the fact that it says קצירך בשדך ושכחת ketzircha besadecha veshachachta
means even if your שכחה shichcha was about בשדך, besadecha, even if
your שכחה shichcha was about stuff that was still standing in the
field, that had not yet been harvested. Okay, so that's what he
does with it. He does not use it to tell you that
it can be even buried. So the רבנן, rabbanan, now the גמרא,
Gemara רבנן שכחת קמה מנא להו? rabbanan shichchat kama mena lahu? If
the רבנן rabbanan learn from the word בשדך besadecha to tell you
buried, where do they learn the idea that if you forget standing
grain that's also part of the מצוה? mitzvah? רבנן שכחת קמה מנא
להו? rabbanan shichchat kama mena lahu? נפקא להו מכי תקצור קצירך בשדך.
nafka lahu miki tikzor ketzircha besadecha. רש"י rashi
says the focus is on מבשדך ושכחת, mibesadecha veshachachta, meaning I think,
wait let me just double-check
רש"י. rashi. מבשדך ושכחת, mibesadecha veshachachta, ושכחת את קצת שדהו. veshachachta et
ketzat sadehu.
Yeah, so they do it from the, oh actually so what I
said for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was what the, what do you
call it,
what רש"י rashi is saying here is for the רבנן. rabbanan. I'm
actually losing track, let's write some of this down. Too many דרשות,
drashot, okay.
So
what is it?
Okay, כי
תקצור
קצירך בשדך
ושכחת.
ki tikzor ketzircha
besadecha veshachachta. Okay, so רבי יהודה would
say, so we said כי תקצור ובשדך, ki tikzor uvesadecha, that juxtaposition
by itself, right, that this is בגלוי, begalui, that's בגלוי, begalui, you
start with the idea of גלוי, galui, okay. And רבי יהודה says
that has to be, and so the רבנן rabbanan say you start
with גלוי galui because it says קצירך. ketzircha. So the fact that
it says
בשדך besadecha tells you for the רבנן rabbanan to, we've already started
this בשדך, besadecha, the רבנן rabbanan would tell you that would tell
you אפילו טמון. afillu tamun.
Okay, that's what they do with
בשדך. besadecha. What does... I should use different colors here. Okay, so
that's what the רבנן Rabbanan do with it. What does ר' יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda do with בשדך? besadecha? So ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda does
with בשדך, besadecha, he says בשדך besadecha means ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
said בשדך. besadecha. So ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says ר' יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda says that it is גלוי, galuy, he goes with the גלוי,
galuy, it has to be exposed. So what he does with the
בשדך besadecha tells you שכחת קמה. shikchas kama.
Okay, that even if it's even if it's just בשדך, besadecha, even
if the grain is just in your field and you know and
it's still standing, that also counts as שכחה. shikcha. Where do the
רבנן Rabbanan get שכחת קמה shikchas kama from? They get it
from the juxtaposition, I said this before for ר' יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda,
but this is what רש"י Rashi says for the רבנן. Rabbanan. They
get it for the juxtaposition of בשדך ושכחת, besadecha veshachachta, meaning בשדך
besadecha tells you buried, but juxtaposing בשדך ושכחת besadecha veshachachta means that
you forgot what was still בשדך. besadecha. So it's the juxtaposition that
tells you שכחת קמה. shikchas kama. Okay, so now we got שכחת
קמה shikchas kama for the רבנן, Rabbanan, the juxtaposition, we got it
for ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda just the word בשדך, besadecha, and that's
where they're debating. Okay, I don't know if you're keeping all that
straight. Moving on. Okay, I don't know if I'm keeping it straight.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: For רבנן, Rabbanan, שכחת קמה מנלן? shikchas kama minalan? נפקא ליה
מכי תקצור קצירך בשדך ושכחת. nafka leih mikitkach shikcha besadecha veshachachta. For
ר' יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, what does ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda do with
the juxtaposition? Now that we're giving significance to this juxtaposition, what does
ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda do with it? For ר' יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda,
מיבעי ליה לכדאמר ר' אבהו, miba'ei leih lechidabiah vavo, ר' אבהו Rebbe
Abahu teaches you, אמר ר' אלעזר דאמר ר' אבהו אמר ר' אלעזר,
Amar Rebbe Elazar de'amar Rebbe Abahu amar Rebbe Elazar, okay, פרט לשצפו
עומרים לתוך שדה, prat leshetzafu omarim letoch sade, שדה חברו. sadeh chavero.
So he emphasizes that שכחה shikcha has to be בשדך. besadecha. You
have to forget something in your field, not in your friend's field.
How would you forget in your friend's field? I bundled a sheaf,
the wind came and blew the sheaf into your field, okay, and
now I forgot that it was in your field. I knew I
was supposed to go and retrieve it or whatever it was, I
forgot it was in your field. Is that שכחה? shikcha? So no,
it has to be ושכחת בשדך. veshachachta besadecha. You have to forget
something in your field, not something that's in your friend's field. Okay,
so that's what it's telling me, not שכחת קמה. shikchas kama. Okay,
so לתוך שדה חברו, letoch sadeh chavero, פרט לשצפו עומרים לתוך שדה
חברו. prat leshetzafu omarim letoch sadeh chavero. רבנן, Rabbanan, מבשדה בשדך. mibsadeh
besadecha.
It's the possessive בשדך. besadecha. So the word שדה sadeh tells me
אפילו טמון, afilu tamun, שדה sadeh juxtaposed to ושכחת veshachachta tells you
שכחת קמה, shikchas kama, that even if the forgetting was while it
was still standing, and the possessive your field tells you only stuff
that's in your field, not in your friend's field. For ר' יהודה,
Rebbe Yehuda, בשדה בשדך לא משמע ליה, bsadeh besadecha lo mashma leih,
and he doesn't make a big deal about the possessive בשדך. besadecha.
Fine, we worked it all out. But bottom line is, yes, it's
a parallel debate by שכחה, shikcha, does it have to be exposed
or can it be buried? But it's maybe based on the context
of that פסוק, and you can't assume that the debate they have
by שכחה shikcha is they would say the same positions when it
would come to, you know, עגלה ערופה. Eglah Arufah? Each one is
explained in the context of the appropriate פסוק. Okay, and as we
have by עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah we do not have any debating
positions, at least so far in our משנה, all we everybody agrees
that it has to be exposed, it can't be buried. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara continues with the ground, which we'll get to. Now
the גמרא Gemara continues with the ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda with the
שכחה shikcha discussion. בעי ר' ירמיה, ba'ei Rebbe Yirmeya, ר' ירמיה Rebbe
Yirmeya asked, ר' ירמיה Rebbe Yirmeya always likes to ask these like
hair-splitting questions. So בעי ר' ירמיה צפו עומרים לתוך שדהו, ba'ei Rebbe
Yirmeya tzafu omarim letoch sadeihu,
your sheaf did not fly into your friend's field. It's in your
field, but it's not on the ground. This is similar to actually
the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah. question, like a guy hanging from the
tree. So it's in your field, it's exposed, but it's not on
the ground. It's let's say on top of a rock or on
top of another sheaf. Does that become שכחה? shikcha? Is it ושכחת
בשדך, veshachachta besadecha, does it have to be on the ground? Okay,
מהו? mahu? What's the הלכה? halacha? אויר שדה כשדה דמי? avir sadeh
kesadeh dami? It's in the airspace, so that's בשדך, besadecha, או לאו
כשדה דמי? o lav kesadeh dami? Or no, בשדך besadecha means it
has to be on the ground of your field? אמר ליה רב
כהנא לרב פפי, amar leih Rav Kahana le-Rav Pappi, so רב כהנא
Rav Kahana said to רב פפי, Rav Pappi, ואמרי ליה רב כהנא
לרב זביד, ve'amrei leih Rav Kahana le-Rav Zevid, תפשוט ליה tifshet leih
mid'Rebbe Abahu, let's learn it out from ר' אבהו Rebbe Abahu אמר
ר' אלעזר, amar Rebbe Elazar, let's learn it out from this הלכה
halacha we just talked about being in your friend's field, דאמר de'amar
who says, פרט לשצפו עומרים לתוך שדה חברו, prat leshetzafu omarim letoch
sadeh chavero, who excludes the case when your sheaf flew into your
friend's field. דחברו אין, dechavero in, so if it's on top of
something in your friend's field you're exempt, לתוך שדהו לא, letoch sadeihu
lo, but if it was in your it was on top of
something in your own field you'd be חייב. chayav. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, that's not what we're talking about. אלא לטעמיך, ela
leta'ameich, לתוך שדה חברו צפו אין מונחים לא? letoch sadeh chavero tzafu
in munachim lo? When it says that they floated into your friend's
field, do you think the exemption is only if it's a sheaf
on top of something else in your friend's field? Let's say your
sheaf flew into your friend's field and it's on the ground. So
do you think that wouldn't be exempt? Of course it would be
exempt. It's not בשדך, besadecha, it's not in your field. So the
word there צפו tzafu does not mean it's on top of something,
that's not the point. The point is it flew out of your
field. Okay, והכי נמי ve-hachinama בשדך. besadecha. והא בעינא בשדך וליכא, veha
beina besadecha veleika, it has to be your field. So when we
say צפו tzafu לתוך שדה חברו, letoch sde chaveiro, the key is
שדה חברו. sde chaveiro. The word צפו tzafu is not meaningful there.
אלא ela לתוך שדה חברו letoch sde chaveiro ואפילו מונחים, va'afilu munachim,
even if it's just on the ground in your friend's field you're
exempt. והאי דקאמר צפו, vehai dekamar tzafu, so why did it say
it floated into your friend's field? דלא משתכח ליה אלא בציפא. delo
mishtakach lei ela betzipa. How else did it get to your friend's
field unless like the wind blew it? But it doesn't mean that
it's suspended on something else. It means it flew into your friend's
field and now it's on the ground. Okay? So you don't know
what the הלכה halacha would be if it's in your field and
it's on top of something else. Okay, so תא שמע, ta shema,
come and
hear. עומר שהחזיק בו להוליכו לעיר, omer shehechzik bo leholicho la'ir, you
took a hold of a sheaf and you're going to bring it
to the to the to the town to sell it. והניחו על
גבי חברו veheniho al gabi chaveiro and you were taking a break
and you put it on your friend's back or excuse me not
friend's back on a fellow on another sheaf. I think it's another
sheaf.
I'm on Joe.
Right, right, right,
yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
I don't know why I said that. On another sheaf. Okay, ושכחו
veshachacho and then you forgot it, you put it down on top
of another sheaf and then you went to take a coffee break
and then you forgot it. Okay, so what's the story?
התחתון hatachton
is sort of like that אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra about כי יחפור
ki yachpor שור רעהו. shorei re'eihu. So he quotes a קראי Karai
that says שור רעהו shorei re'eihu means his fellow שור. shore. So
אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra says אין לשור ריע אלא בן זוטא בלבד.
ein leshor re'a ela Ben Zuta bilvad. I think the guy's name
was בן זוטא Ben Zuta בלבד. bilvad. I think whatever the guy's
name was. Anyway, okay fine. Anyway, so you put it on a
fellow sheaf. Okay, anyway he puts it on top of another sheaf.
Okay, so and then he forgot about it. So what's the story?
Is the and then you also forgot about the bottom sheaf because
now the bottom sheaf is buried. Okay,
so is which one of those is שכחה? shichecha? So let's take
a look.
Okay. ושכחו התחתון שכחה והעליון אינו שכחה. veshachacho hatachton shichecha veha'elyon eino
shichecha. The bottom one is שכחה, shichecha, okay, because you genuinely forgot
about it, but not the top. And we're assuming not the top
because it is not on the ground. רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר
משום רבי שמעון שניהם אינם שכחה. Rabbi Shimon Ben Yehuda omer mishum
Rabbi Shimon shneihem einam shichecha. They're both not. התחתון מפני שהוא טמון,
hatachton mipnei shehu tamun, it's buried, right, that's what we've been discussing,
so the bottom one is buried. והעליון מפני שהוא צף, veha'elyon mipnei
shehu tzaf, and the top one because it is suspended and floating.
So everybody agrees the top one is not, they're debating whether there's
an exemption of buried, that's what we saw, right, whether there's an
exemption of buried by שכחה shichecha is a debate, but they all
agree the top one is not presumably because it's not on the
ground, it's floating. So the גמרא Gemara says עד כאן לא פליגי
אלא בתחתון. ad kan lo peligi ela betachton. They're only debating the
bottom one, whether there's an exemption of buried. אבל בעליון, aval be'elyon,
the top one, דברי הכל לא הוי שכחה, divrei hakol lo havei
shichecha, everybody says it's not presumably because it's only in the air,
it's not on the ground. So that's a pretty good resolution. הגמרא
Gemara says no. שאני התם כיון דאחזיק בה זכה
בה. shani hatam keivan de'achzik bah zachah bah. No, no, no, there
it's not שכחה shichecha because you took possession of it. You picked
up the sheaf in order to bring it to town. So that's
not forgetting it, you already actually possessed it. Okay now you could
say you always possess it, it's your stuff, but there's an assumption
that once you actually take possession of it in that physical way,
it doesn't become שכחה shichecha after that point. Okay and it has
nothing to do with the fact that it's floating. So the גמרא
Gemara says אי הכי מאי איריא על גבי חברו? ei hachi mai
irya al gabi chaveiro? So then if that's true, why did he
give the scenario that you put it on top of another sheaf?
אפילו בשדה נמי, afilu basadeh nami, he could have even just put
it down. The real point of that teaching should have been once
you took possession of it, it can't be שכחה. shichecha. It's not
because it's on top of something. הגמרא Gemara says אין הכי נמי,
ein hachi nami, you're right we could have said that. והא דקתני
על גבי חברו, veha dekatana al gabi chaveiro, so why'd we give
the scenario that you put it on top of another sheaf? משום
תחתון, mishum tachton,
because we wanted to discuss the status of the bottom sheaf. Is
the bottom sheaf considered טמון tamun and is the bottom sheaf exempt?
But for the top sheaf it has nothing to do with the
fact that it's on top, it just has to do with the
fact that you took possession. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
if that's true, והא מפני שהוא צף קאמר. veha mipnei shehu tzaf
kamar.
But what do you mean? But it says that the top is
exempt because it is floating, because it's suspended. So it seems like
that's the reason. Which is a pretty good point. So the גמרא
Gemara: says אימא מפני שהוא כצף. eima mipnei shehu ketzaf. It's like
it's floating. What does that mean? רש"י Rashi says it's like you
never put it down, it's like it's still in your hands. Once
you took possession of it it remains in your possession. Okay that's
a pretty weak read, you know, the simple sense is that it
really is saying that the fact that it's off the ground exempts
it. But the גמרא Gemara has gotten out of that proof and
said the exemption there is not based on the fact that it's
off the ground, the exemption there is based on the fact that
it is you've taken possession. Again the parallel I should say to
עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah. עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah. we do know, if
it's not on the ground, it's not you know you don't do
the whole ritual, right? If the guy is hanging from a tree
you don't do the ritual. So both of these are parallel, the
buried and the off the ground. But what we're exploring is while
we know that's exempt by the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah we're exploring
if that's exempt by שכחה. shichecha. Okay.
But if it's on a rock that's on the ground?
I don't know that's a good question. What would count because here
it's בשדה, basadeh, so a rock might not be בשדה, basadeh, but
a rock might still be... באדמה, Ba'adamah, I'm not sure exactly what
the line would be. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. So we still don't know the answer, but
now we're going to sort of circle back to it. So אביי
Abaye said, and here's a statement that occurs a few times in
the גמרא: Gemara הריני כבן עזאי בשוקי טבריה. Hareini k'Ben Azai b'shukei
Tveria.
I am feeling so good about myself and about my learning, I
feel like בן עזאי, Ben Azai, right, when he was in Tiberias
and in the marketplaces and would be teaching תורה Torah and like
anybody could challenge him, you know, I feel the same way. Like,
he's got... I'm going to take on all challenges, ask me any
question. Okay, so if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says,
he says where's רש"י? Rashi? הריני כבן עזאי, Hareini k'Ben Azai, like
for twelve lines on the bottom. יום אחד היה דעתו צלולה, Yom
echad haya da'ato tzlula, he was feeling very good, אמר הריני כאן
בפומבדיתא מוכן להשיב לדבר לשואל בעומק ובחריפות. Amar hareini kan b'Pumbedita muchan
lehashiv le'davar l'sho'el be'omek u'vecharifut.
I can answer, I can take on any question, כבן עזאי שהחריף
ודרש בשוקי טבריה. k'Ben Azai she'hecharif v'darash b'shukei Tveria. All
right, so now, you know, that's like a challenge. Let's see if
we can stump him. All right, so אמר ליה רבה בר אבא
לאביי, Amar lei Rabbah bar Abba l'Abaye, so one of the rabbis
said to אביי, Abaye, here's a question I got for you. שני
חללים זה על גבי זה. Shenei chalalim zeh al gabei zeh. Now
we're going to shift from the sheaves to the on top of
one another to corpses. You have two corpses, one lying on top
of another. Okay, מהיכן הוא מודד? Meihechan hu moded? Where which one
where do you measure from in terms of the עגלה ערופה? eglah
arufah. Which corpse, or if either or if both, have a status
for doing the ritual of the עגלה ערופה? egla arufa, Do you
say מין במינו הוי טמון? Min b'mino havei tamun? Is the bottom
one considered buried? Why would it not be buried? Well is being
buried under another corpse considered buried? Is מין במינו Min b'mino considered
buried
and then the bottom one would not have the status for עגלה
ערופה? ומין במינו לא הוי צף? U'min b'mino lavei tzaf? And how
about the top one? Because we also know by עגלה ערופה that
you're exempt if something is suspended. Okay, so do you say that
if it's under a corpse, it's still considered buried, but ומין במינו
לא הוי צף, U'min b'mino lavei tzaf, but if you're on top
of a corpse, it's not considered suspended? So maybe there's a different
determination of the definition of buried and suspended if you're buried by
a corpse or suspended by a corpse. Okay, so would we say
that way? ומעליון מודד. U'me'elyon moded. So the top one would not
be considered suspended, the top one would be considered on the ground,
but the bottom one would not have a status, that would be
considered buried. או דילמא, O dilma, or do you say, מין במינו
הוי צף ומין במינו לא הוי טמון, Min b'mino havei tzaf u'min
b'mino lavei tamun, the reverse? Okay, that the top one is considered
floating, the fact that it's on a corpse doesn't get it out
of that designation, but the bottom one is not considered buried because
it's only buried under a corpse. Okay, and therefore ומתחתון מודד, U'mi'tachton
moded, so the bottom one is the one with the status. או
דילמא, O dilma, or do you say, מין במינו הוי טמון ומין
במינו הוי צף, Min b'mino havei tamun u'min b'mino havei tzaf, it's
both considered buried and suspended? לא מתחתון מודד ולא מעליון מודד, Lo
mi'tachton moded v'lo me'elyon moded, and neither of them have the status.
No עגלה ערופה.
No עגלה ערופה. And of course, he didn't give the fourth example,
but רש"י Rashi fills in: or it's both considered not buried and
not suspended and both of them are an עגלה ערופה. Two עגלה
ערופה עגלות, Eglot, and maybe from different cities, maybe one corpse is
closer to one city and the other to another. So אמר ליה,
Amar lei, okay, so that was the question, that was the stumper.
Let's see what he was able to answer.
Can I ask you a question? Yes. You measure from the head
or from the...?
That's coming up. It's coming up. Coming up. Coming up. Hold on,
it's coming up. Okay. תניתוה. Tanituha.
So he said we learned it,
he's going to do it by analogy to the case of the
sheaf. עומר שהחזיק בו להוליכו לעיר, Omer she'hechizik bo le'holicho la'ir, he
took hold of this sheaf to bring to the city, והניחו על
גבי חברו ושכחו. ve'hinnicho al gabei chaveiro ve'shachacho. התחתון שכחה והעליון אינו
שכחה. Ha-tachton shichcha ve-ha-elyon eino shichcha. So
the bottom one is שכחה, shichcha, so you see at least the
idea that... okay, and the top one is not. The top one
is not, maybe because of the idea that you took possession, but
the bottom one, the first teaching is שכחה. shichcha. רבי שמעון בן
יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון שניהם אינם שכחה. Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda
omer mishum Rabbi Shimon sheneihem einam shichcha. They're both not. התחתון מפני
שהוא טמון והעליון מפני שהוא צף. Ha-tachton mipnei she-hu tamun ve-ha-elyon mipnei
she-hu tzaf. Now, so what they're debating is is the top one...
everybody agrees the top one is exempt, they're debating whether the bottom
one is exempt. So what's that debate about? So the גמרא Gemara
says, סברוה הני תנאי כרבי יהודה סבירא להו. Savruha hanei tanna'ei k'Rabbi
Yehuda sevira lehu.
They both hold like רבי יהודה, דאמר בשדה פרט לטמון. de'amar Basadeh
pratt l'tamun. They both agree to the principle that buried by שכחה
shichcha is exempt. And if that's true, what are they debating? מאי
לאו בהא קמיפלגי? Mai lav be'ha kamiflagi? This seems to be what
they are debating, whether buried under a similar object is considered buried.
דמר סבר מין במינו הוי טמון. De'mar savar min b'mino havei tamun.
It is considered buried even if it's buried under another sheaf. ומר
סבר לא הוי טמון. U'mar savar lavei tamun. It's not buried. So
meaning I don't know the answer to the question about the top
one, whether the top one on top of another similar object is
considered floating or not, because maybe the עומר omer case is not
about floating the top one, maybe it's about having taken possession, but
at least whether the bottom one is considered buried, that seems to
be this debate. I don't know what the הלכה למעשה halacha l'ma'aseh
answer is, but I can tell you that that seems to be
this debate, that they presumably both agree buried is exempt and they're
debating whether it's considered buried. So that's what he said, that seems
to be this debate. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא. So the גמרא Gemara, says that's not necessarily true. אי כרבי
יהודה סבירא להו, Ei k'Rabbi Yehuda sevira lehu, I'll tell you that
if they both held like רבי יהודה that טמון tamun was an
exemption, דכולי עלמא de'kulei alma
Everybody would say that it is considered buried. והכא בפלוגתא דרבי יהודה
ורבנן מיפלגי. ve-hacha bi-plugeta d'Rebbi Yehuda ve-Rabbanan mi-pleigi. Maybe they're just disagreeing
in the principle of whether buried is an exemption. דרבנן כרבנן, de-Rabbanan
ke-Rabbanan, the rabbis hold like the other rabbis that buried is considered
is not an exemption, ורבי שמעון בן יהודה כרבי יהודה, ve-Rebbi Shimon
ben Yehuda ke-Rebbi Yehuda, and Rebbi Shimon ben Yehuda works out very
nicely, he holds like his father, like Rebbi Yehuda, and holds that
buried is an exemption. So meaning, is it true that there's somebody
here that says buried under a similar thing is buried? Yes, that's
Rebbi Shimon ben Yehuda's position. What is the other position? The other
position might not be debating whether it's considered buried. The other position
might be debating whether there's such an exemption of buried altogether when
it comes to שכחה. shikh'cha. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, if
that's true that they're debating whether there's an exemption of buried, אי
הכי מאי איריא גבי חברו, ee hachi mai irya gabei chaveiro, why
give the scenario of under another sheaf? Just give a more simple
case, אפילו בעפר ובצרור נמי, afilu be-afar u-bi-tzror nami, just talk about
under dirt if you want to say there's no exemption of buried.
The גמרא Gemara says אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, you're right.
To tell you there's no exemption of buried we could have given
a more extreme case, even under dirt it's not exempt. ואודיעך כוחו
דרבי יהודה, ve-odi'acha kocho d'Rebbi Yehuda, why do we give the case
of under a sheaf? To tell you the חידוש chiddush of the
one who says that there is an exemption of buried, דאמר אפילו
מין במינו הוי טמון, d'amar afilu min be-mino havei tamun, not only
is there an exemption of buried, but even under a sheaf would
still be considered buried. Okay, so bottom line is there clearly is
a position that מין במינו min be-mino is טמון, tamun, that's Rebbi
Shimon ben Yehuda. You don't know if the חכמים Chachamim disagree with
the definition of טמון tamun or if they just disagree with whether
or not טמון tamun applies by שכחה. shikh'cha. Okay, let's just try
to get to the משנה here. Okay, let's see if we can
do it. תנו רבנן. חלל, chalal. a corpse, ולא, v'lo, and חלל
chalal is understood to be like by sword, בחלל חרב, be-chalal cherev,
ולא חנוק, v'lo chanuk, not just strangled. חלל, chalal a corpse, ולא
מפרפר באדמה, v'lo mefarper ba-adamah, he has to be fully like laying
still, not that he's still
thrashing. Okay, ולא מפרפר באדמה v'lo mefarper ba-adamah on the ground, ולא
טמון, v'lo tamun, not buried, בגל, be-gal, under under a pile. נופל,
nofel, falling, ולא תלוי באילן, v'lo talui be-ilan, not suspended from a
tree. בשדה, ba-sadeh, in the field, ולא צף על פני המים, v'lo
tzaf al p'nei ha-mayim, not on the floating on water. רבי אלעזר
אומר, Rebbi Elazar omer, בכולן אם היו חלל עורפין. be-chulan im hayu
chalal orfin. Actually the only word that he cares about is חלל.
chalal If it's it has to be an actual like corpse, presumably
by a sword, that I'll agree with, he says. But these other
things like that it has to be it can't be thrashing or
it has to be exposed, whatever, that I don't agree. Once it's
a חלל chalal you would do it. I don't have these technical
exemptions. תניא ושנו ברייתא, Tanya v'shanu braisa, אמרו לו לרבי אלעזר, amru
lo l'Rebbi Elazar, they said to Rebbi Elazar, אי
אתה מודה שאם היה חנוק ומוטל באשפה שאין עורפין? ee ata modeh
she-im haya chanuk u-mutal be-ashpah she-ein orfin? Look, you at least agree
with the חלל chalal point, you would agree that if he were
strangled and he was there on the garbage heap that you would
not do it, no matter how horrific that would be, you agree
to the exemption of חלל that it has to be by the
sword, strangled you wouldn't. So therefore why don't you say the same
thing about these issues about like buried and suspended? Why do you
disagree with us there? אלמא, almah, explains the גמרא, חלל ולא חנוק,
chalal v'lo chanuk, you agree to the דרשה drasha of חלל and
not strangled. הכא נמי באדמה ולא טמון בגל, hacha nami ba-adamah v'lo
tamun be-gal, נופל ולא תלוי באילן, nofel v'lo talui be-ilan, בשדה ולא
צף על גבי מים, ba-sadeh v'lo tzaf al gabei mayim, you should
agree with us to the other דרשות. drashot. So Rebbi Elazar, חלל
יתירה כתיב, chalal yeteira k'tiv, no, he says, look, it says the
word חלל many many times in that פרשה. parsha. So that דרשה
drasha I agree with. But the נופל באדמה nofel ba-adamah whatever, I
don't give weight to that, that that's me making these technical exclusions.
Okay, let's put a finish to the משנה. נמצא סמוך לספר או
לעיר שרובה גוים, nimtza samuch l'sefar o l'ir she-rubah goyim,
if it's near a a
town on the border or it's a near a town that has
a lot of that's that's majority non-Jews, you would not do עגלה
ערופה. Why not? דכתיב כי ימצא, d'chtiv ki yimatzei,
if you happen to find, פרט למצוי, perat l'matzui, as opposed to
if it's very common. So if a border town there's all constant
border skirmishes with say, you know, with a
belligerent country that you're bordering, there's going to be a lot of
corpses. And the גמרא's assumption in terms of the non-Jews, you know,
they were living under the Romans and so on, there was an
assumption that there would be unfortunately a lot of a lot of
murders. או לעיר שאין בה בית דין, o l'ir she-ein bah beis
din, or if it was next to a city without a בית
דין you wouldn't do it, דבעינא זקני העיר, d'ba'ina ziknei ha-ir, because
the elders of the city have to come out, וליכא. v'leika. ואזיל
ואומר, v'azil v'omer, and then final point says, אין מודדין אלא לעיר,
ein modedin ela l'ir, you only measure when you measure to the
nearby town, you don't go to the nearest town, any near town,
you go to the nearest town that has a בית דין. So
the גמרא says פשיטא, p'shita, obviously you go to the nearest town
that has a בית דין. כיון דתנא לעיר שאין בה בית דין,
keivan d'tana l'ir she-ein bah beis din, since you don't do it
with a city without a בית דין, ענין דאין מודדין אלא לעיר
שיש בה בית דין, inyan d'ein modedin ela l'ir she-yesh bah beis
din, obviously you only go to a town that has a בית
דין. No, הא קא משמע לן, ha ka mashma lan, it's teaching
us כדתניא. k'datanya. Imagine נמצא סמוך לעיר שאין בה בית דין, nimtza
samuch l'ir she-ein bah beis din,
let's say the closest town does not have a בית דין. You
have two possibilities: you go to the closest town with a בית
דין or you don't do it all together, right? So שאין בית
דין שמניחין אותו, she-ein beis din she-manichin oto, how do I know
that I pass... Pass over that town, ומודדים לעיר שיש בה בית
דין, u-moddim le-ir she-yesh bah beis din, but I still do the
מדידה, medidah, I do עגלה ערופה, but I just go to the
city with the בית דין. How do you know that? תלמוד לומר
Talmud lomar ולקחו זקני העיר ההיא ve-lakchu ziknei ha-ir ha-hi מכל מקום.
mi-kol makom. Somehow the דרשה derasha of ולקחו, ve-lakchu, I don't exactly
get the דרשה, derasha, but somehow it means that even if it's
not the city that's closest, but it's the closest city with a
בית דין, that is the city that participates in this ritual. Okay,
we'll end with that,
which the exegesis is a bit strange, because usually it's like every
individual word.
Right. And here it's just the majority, right, it says a lot.
It's also funny, it's also funny because if the closest city is
somehow supposed to be the city that, or the town, the one
that's most likely to have had the murderer among them, then the
fact that you go to the city with the בית דין, that
doesn't mean that they're the most likely. They're the ones that can
take responsibility for it, because they have a בית דין to symbolically
take responsibility for it.
Exactly, the issue is responsibility needs to be kept at the center,
even if you can't.